Hey there, ready for a quick grammar workout?
こんにちは、短い文法の練習を始めましょうか？
Today, we're going to master one of the most useful words in English, when.
今日は英語で最も便利な単語の一つ、「when」をマスターします。
We're going to figure out exactly how to ask about time, dates, and schedules, so you
時間、日付、スケジュールについての質問の仕方を学びます。
can do it with total confidence. Let's dive right in.
自信を持ってできるようになります。それでは始めましょう。
So let's start with a classic. When is your birthday?
まずは定番の質問から。あなたの誕生日はいつですか？
It's a really simple, friendly question, right?
とてもシンプルで親しみやすい質問ですね。
But the way it's built, that's the key to unlocking hundreds of other questions.
でも、この構造が他の多くの質問を作る鍵になります。
By the end of this, you'll see the pattern and you'll be able to ask this and so
最後にはパターンが見えて、これができるようになります。
so much more. All right, here's our game plan for today.
さあ、今日の計画を見てみましょう。
We'll start with how to ask when, then we'll cover the two main rules.
まず「when」を使った質問の仕方を学び、その後、2つの主要なルールを説明します。
After that, we'll put it to the desk, build up your time toolkit with some vocabulary,
その後、実践して、語彙を増やし、便利なチートシートでまとめます。始めましょう！
and wrap it all up with a handy cheat sheet. Let's get to it!
では、核心に入っていきましょう。
Okay, let's get to the core of it.
「when」を使った質問は実はとても体系的です。
Asking questions with when is actually really systematic.
思っているほど難しくはありません。
It's not as tricky as you might think.
学ぶべきパターンは2つだけで、使う動詞の種類によります。
There are really just two main patterns to learn, and it all depends on the type
一つずつ分解してみましょう。
of verb you're using. Let's break them down one by one.
まずはB動詞を使った質問について話しましょう。
First up, let's talk about questions with B verbs.
isやareのような言葉です。
You know, words like is and are.
これはとてもシンプルな3ステップのプロセスです。
It's a super simple three-step process.
まず、普通の文から始めます。
First, you start with a plain old statement.
あなたの誕生日は8月7日です。
Your birthday is August 7th.
これをはい・いいえの質問にするには、最初の2語を入れ替えます。
To make that a yes or no question, you just flip the first two words.
あなたの誕生日は8月7日ですか？
Is your birthday August 7th?
そして、最後のステップで「when」を最初に置きます。
And then, for the final step, you just stick when right at the beginning.
あなたの誕生日はいつですか？簡単ですね。
When is your birthday? See? Simple as that.
次はルール2です。
And now for rule number two.
これは行動動詞、playやstudy、goのような言葉に関するものです。
You know what? The process is almost exactly the same.
実は、プロセスはほとんど同じです。
You start with your statement, you play tennis on Sundays.
まず、あなたの文から始めます。あなたは日曜日にテニスをします。
Now to make it a yes-no question, you add do at the start.
これをはい・いいえの質問にするには、最初に「do」を加えます。
Do you play tennis on Sundays? And then? You guessed it.
あなたは日曜日にテニスをしますか？そして？その通りです。
You just pop when on the front. When do you play tennis?
「when」を前に置くだけです。あなたはいつテニスをしますか？
This pattern is incredibly useful.
このパターンは非常に便利です。
So here it is, the key difference, side by side.
では、ここで重要な違いを並べてみましょう。
For B verbs, you're going to use when, with is, or are.
B動詞の場合は、isやareと一緒にwhenを使います。
For all those action verbs, you'll use when, with do, or does.
行動動詞の場合は、doやdoesと一緒にwhenを使います。
It's kind of like a fork in the road.
まるで分かれ道のようです。
Once you know which path to take for your verb, you're totally set.
どの動詞の道を選ぶかを知れば、全てが整います。
So if you remember one thing, make it this, the golden rule.
もし一つだけ覚えることがあるなら、これがゴールデンルールです。
Every single when question is just the word when plus a regular yes-no question.
すべての「when」質問は、whenという単語と通常のはい・いいえの質問の組み合わせです。
That's it.
それだけです。
If you know how to form a yes-no question, you can now ask any when question you want.
はい・いいえの質問の作り方を知っていれば、どんな「when」質問でもできます。
Definitely keep this little formula in your back pocket.
この小さな公式はぜひ覚えておいてください。
All right, talk is cheap.
さて、話はここまで。
You've learned the rules, and now it's time to put that knowledge into action.
ルールを学んだので、今度はその知識を実践する時間です。
Let's do a couple of quick challenges just to make sure these ideas really stick.
いくつかの簡単なチャレンジをして、アイデアを定着させましょう。
You ready? Okay, here's your first challenge.
準備はいいですか？では、最初のチャレンジです。
Unscramble these words to make a proper question.
これらの単語を並べ替えて、正しい質問を作ってください。
Now think back to our rule for B verbs. I'll give you a second.
B動詞のルールを思い出してみてください。少し考えてみてください。
And there's the answer. When is your father's birthday?
答えはこれです。あなたのお父さんの誕生日はいつですか？
Did you see the pattern?
パターンが見えましたか？
When plus the yes-no question is your father's birthday.
whenとはい・いいえの質問が組み合わさっています。
job if you got that right. Okay, challenge number two.
正解なら素晴らしいです。次はチャレンジ2です。
This one has an action verb in it, play.
こちらは動作動詞のplayが含まれています。
How would you put these words together to make a perfect question?
これらの単語をどう組み合わせて完璧な質問を作りますか？
Take a moment.
少し考えてみてください。
The correct answer is, when does your brother play the violin?
正しい答えは、あなたの兄はいつバイオリンを弾きますか？
And again, check out that structure, when, followed by the yes-no question, does your
そして、またその構造を見てください。whenの後に、はい・いいえの質問が続きます。
brother play the violin?
あなたの兄はバイオリンを弾きますか？
See, you are definitely getting the hang of this.
いい感じにコツをつかんできてるね。
And for our final challenge, let's match a question to the right answer.
最後のチャレンジは、質問に正しい答えを合わせることだ。
The question is, when is St. Valentine's Day?
質問は、聖バレンタインデーはいつか？
Take a look at the options. Which one, A, B, or C, is the best fit?
選択肢を見て、A、B、Cの中でどれが最適か考えてみて。
And the answer is C. It's February 14th, so why is that the right one?
答えはC。2月14日だから、これが正解なのはなぜ？
Well, the question asks for a specific date. In April is just a month,
質問は特定の日付を求めている。4月はただの月で、
and on Saturdays is a repeating day.
土曜日は繰り返しの日だ。
C is the only one that gives us that exact date. Excellent work.
Cだけがその正確な日付を示している。素晴らしい仕事だ。
So now you're pretty much an expert at asking when.
これで「いつ」を聞くのはほぼ専門家だね。
Let's build up your toolkit for answering those questions.
次は、その質問に答えるためのツールを増やそう。
Here's some of that essential time-related vocabulary
必要な時間に関する基本的な語彙を紹介するよ。
you're gonna need.
これが必要になるからね。
First up, the absolute basics, the days of the week.
まずは基本中の基本、曜日だ。
You can use these to answer questions like, when do you play tennis?
これを使って、テニスはいつするの？といった質問に答えられる。
You could say, I play tennis on Saturdays.
「土曜日にテニスをする」と言えるよ。
Knowing these is just fundamental for talking about your weekly plans.
これを知っておくことは、週の予定を話す上で基本だ。
Next up in the toolkit, we have the months of the year.
次に、ツールキットには月も含まれる。
From January all the way to December,
1月から12月まで、
these are what you'll use for birthdays, holidays,
誕生日や祝日、特定の日付に使う。
and any kind of specific date. Like, when is your birthday?
例えば、誕生日はいつ？「8月だよ」と。
Oh, it's in August. These are a must have.
これは必須だね。
And finally, we've got the four seasons. Spring, summer, fall, and you'll hear people say autumn
最後に、四季がある。春、夏、秋、そして秋と言う人もいる。
too. In winter. These are perfect for talking about bigger chunks of time. You know, for a
冬もね。これらは長い期間について話すのに最適だ。
question like, when are you going on vacation? In the summer! Wow, we've covered a lot. So let's
例えば、「いつ休暇に行くの？」と聞かれたら、「夏だよ！」と。
wrap it all up with a really simple cheat sheet you can use to remember everything we've talked
たくさんのことをカバーしたね。では、
about today. And here it is, the when cheat sheet. It's so simple. For b-verbs, the structure
今日話したことを覚えるための簡単なチートシートでまとめよう。
is when plus is R, like our example, when is your birthday?
これが「いつ」のチートシート。とてもシンプルだよ。b動詞の場合、
And for action verbs, it's when plus do does, just like in when do you play tennis?
構造は「when + is / are」で、例えば「誕生日はいつ？」
Seriously, this one slide, that's the whole lesson in a nutshell.
動詞の場合は「when + do / does」で、「テニスはいつする？」のように。
So there you have it. We've broken it all down.
このスライド一枚で、レッスン全体がまとめられている。
We've practiced and we've reviewed.
これで全てを整理したね。
You now have the structure, the rules, and the vocabulary.
練習もして、復習もした。
The only question left is, what are you going to do with it?
構造、ルール、語彙が揃った。
Now that you know how to ask, what's the first when question you want to ask?
残る質問は、これをどう活用するかだ。
Go out there and give it a try. Thanks for joining me today.
聞き方がわかった今、最初に聞きたい「いつ」の質問は何？